# Biniyam Tiruye

Ph.D. pre-candidate - Computer Science and Engineering, University of Michigan 2260 Hayward St., Ann Arbor MI 48109-2121, USA (734) 968-7549 | btiruye@umich.edu

## **Biography**

Interested in building the computing systems of tomorrow with security and privacy as core components by exploiting advancements in both software and hardware. Much of my research focuses on designing systems with a robust defense against attacks based on memory access patterns and maintaining the secrecy of private data through algorithm-level modifications to programs.

#### Education

**University of Michigan** 

Ann Arbor, MI

Ph.D in Computer Science and Engineering, GPA: 4.0/4.0

Sept 2021 - PRESENT

- Advisor: Prof. Todd Austin, Concentration: Security & Privacy.

#### **Addis Ababa University**

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

BSc in Software Engineering, GPA: 3.85/4.0

Sept 2015 - Jun 2020

Relevant Coursework: Comp Architecture, Advanced Computer Security,
 Operating Systems, Data Structure, and Algorithm, Robotics, Systems Programming.

 Gem5
 Davis, CA

 Gem5 Boot Camp 2022
 Jul 11 - Jul 15, 2022

- Gem5 training for junior computer architecture researchers.

**10 Academy**Data Science Training

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia

Jul 2020 - Oct 2020

- Data science training on data analysis, modeling, and deployment.

#### **Publications**

#### **Under Review**

 Exploring the Efficiency of Data-Oblivious Programs, IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Code Generation and Optimization (CGO 2023).

Details the first performance characterization of data-oblivious programs and studies mechanical data-oblivious transformations applied to twenty workloads.

## **Professional Experience**

#### Center for Application Driving Architecture (ADA)

Ann Arbor, MI Sept 2021 - PRESENT

Graduate Research Assistant, University of Michigan

AI.Science

Full-stack web developer

Totonto, Canada Jan 2021 - Aug 2021

**University of Michigan** 

Undergraduate researcher

Ann Arbor, MI May 2019 - Aug 2019

#### **Extracurricular Activities**

ITSC InspireAddis Ababa, EthiopiaCo-founder & President, Addis Ababa UniversityMar 2018 - Mar 2019

- Cofounded ITSC-Inspire, a student-led youth association in Addis Ababa University. I was the president for a year and organized hackathons, seminars, guest talks, and other Events.

## **Teaching Experience**

#### **ITSE-2122 Mobile Programming**

Primary Instructor, Addis Ababa University

Addis Ababa, Ethiopia Sept 2020 - Jan 2021

## **Research Projects**

#### **Data Oblivious Compiler**

A C++ compiler that converts native programs into their Data Oblivious versions using Clang source-to-source transformation.

#### FRAME: Automated Persistent Memory Reverse Engineering Tool

An automated, graphical tool for executing reverse engineering tests on persistent memory modules.

### **Making Private Computations Faster with Efficient ORAMs**

An evaluation of Oblivious RAMs (ORAMs) in the context of Privacy Enhanced Computation.

#### Skills

**Programming:** C/C++, Python, Java, Java Script, Bash Script,

Simulations: Gem5

Compiler: LLVM, CLANG

Operating Systems: Linux, Windows, macOS

Web Development: HTML/CSS, ReactJs, NodeJs, GraphQL, SQL, TypeScript

Design: Photoshop, Adobe XD, UI/UX design, Graphic Design

Other: Git, Android